A Guide to the George Wythe Munford Papers, 1828-1891
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
George Wythe Munford Papers, 1828-1891
The Library of Virginia
21731
143 pages
George Wythe Munford
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Purchased from Charles Talbott of Richmond, Virginia, 22 May 1940.
Biographical Information
George Wythe Munford was born 8 January 1803 in Richmond, Virginia to William Munford (1775-1825) and Sally Radford Munford. Educated at the College of William & Mary, Munford was employed by his father who served as clerk of the Virginia House of Delegates. Munford succeeded to the post of clerk upon his father's death in 1825 and held that position in 1852, when he became Secretary of the Commonwealth, serving in that position for 12 years. He also served as clerk of the Virginia Constitutional Convention of 1829-1830. Munford married first, Lucy Singleton Taylor (1802-1834) 20 November 1828, and second, Elizabeth Thorowgood Ellis (1818-1900) 29 November 1838. Munford died in Richmond 10 January 1882 and was buried in Hollywood Cemetery.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1828-1891, of George Wythe Munford (1803-1882) of Richmond, Virginia, consisting of correspondence concerning a duel challenge; the 1860 Democratic convention in Baltimore, Maryland, and secession; John Thompson Brown (1802-1836); a portrait of George Wythe Munford for the Virginia State Library; gold for the Virginia treasury; George W. Munford's legal troubles with the federal government; society; the Buchanan Spring Quoit Club; and other matters. Papers also include affidavit and deed for Richmond property; bills, checks, and drafts for caterers; stock certificate; military general orders concerning the Confederate archives, Henry H. Wells's appointment as Governor of Virginia, election on the proposed constitution, and transfer of power to civilian authority; a eulogy on George W. Munford; questions for former Confederates seeking pardons; and two sermons by Reverend John Buchanan (d. 1822), rector of St. John's Church in Richmond.
Contents List
- Letter, 3 January 1828, from John Hampden Pleasants (1797-1846) of Richmond, Virginia, to an unknown correspondent challenging him to a duel. (Folder 1)
- Affidavit, 2 February 1833, by Thomas Rutherford (1766-1852) placing a value on property owned by Mrs. Thomas Taylor, both of Richmond, Virginia. Includes note by Charles Talbott concerning the item. (Folder 1)
- Deed, dated 2 January 1837 and recorded 5 May 1837, for a lot in Richmond from Thomas and Sarah Rutherford to George Wythe Munford. Includes note by Charles Talbott concerning the item. (Folder 1)
- Menu or bill, 30 June 1838, of caterers for Barbecue Club by George Wythe Munford. The Barbecue Club was the Buchanan Spring Quoit Club. (Folder 1)
- Bill, 2 June 1842, of caterers for the Barbecue Club. (Folder 1)
- Check, 22 August 1846, payable to caterers, drawn on the Farmers' Bank of Virginia. Probably payment for services to the Barbecue Club. (Folder 1)
- Draft, 10 October 1846, payable to caterers drawn on the Farmers' Bank. Probably payment for services to the Barbecue Club. (Folder 1)
- Draft, 19 May 1848, payable to the Barbecue Club drawn on the Farmers' Bank. (Folder 1)
- Letter, 22 June 1860, from Powhatan Ellis (1790-1863) of Mississippi and Richmond, Virginia, to Charles Ellis (1817-1900) of Richmond, Virginia, discussing family news and the Democratic Convention in Baltimore, Maryland. Contains a brief note on Powhatan Ellis. (Folder 1)
- Letter, 26 July 1861, from Powhatan Ellis to Charles Ellis reflecting on secession. (Folder 1)
- Letter, 9 August 1861, from Powhatan Ellis to Charles Ellis reflecting on secession. (Folder 1)
- Certificate of stock, 17 October 1863, from the Confederate States of America to Munford for $8250. (Folder 1)
- General Orders #3, 25 April 1865, concerning the archives of the former Confederate government. (Folder 1)
- General Orders #3, 4 April 1868, appointing Henry H. Wells (1823-1900) governor of Virginia. (Folder 1)
- General Orders #104, 8 September 1869, announcing the official results of the elections on the proposed constitution. (Folder 1)
- General Order #10, 28 January 1870, transferring authority from the military to civil administration. (Folder 1)
- Letter, 26 July 1870, from Munford to Thomas P. Atkinson of Danville, Virginia, regarding John Thompson Brown (1802-1836). (Folder 1)
- Draft of a letter, [1870], about John Thompson Brown. Includes a note concerning Munford and Brown by Charles Talbott. (Folder 1)
- Letter, 5 October 1875, from William P. Munford to James McDonald, Secretary of the Commonwealth, presenting a portrait of George Wythe Munford to the Virginia State Library. (Folder 1)
- Letter, 5 October 1875, from James McDonald to William Munford thanking him for the portrait. (Folder 1)
- Communication, 27 February 1877, from Governor James Lawson Kemper in relation to gold turned over to the Virginia treasury. Printed as Senate document No. XVII. (Folder 1)
- Letter, 14 March 1877, from George Munford to Beverley Tucker requesting assistance in a suit against him by the Federal government. (Folder 1)
- Letter, 22 March 1877, from Munford to Lieutenant Governor Henry Wirtz Thomas (1812-1890) concering the Federal government's suit against him and former Governor William Smith (1797-1887) and containing statements from Munford and Smith. (Folder 1)
- Letter, 2 April 1877, from Munford to Tucker again concerning his legal difficulties. (Folder 1)
- Letter, 13 October 1881, from Robert A. Brock (1839-1914) to Thomas Harding Ellis (1814-1898) commenting on society. (Folder 2)
- Eulogy, 6 February 1882, by Thomas H. Ellis about George W. Munford. Pages 1-9 are missing. (Folder 2)
- Letter, 28 January 1890 [sic], from Ellis to Charles Ellis (1817-1900) discussing family matters and includes a copy of a letter, dated 16 January 1891, from Ellis to William A. Palmer reminiscing about the Buchanan Spring Quoit Club. (Folder 2)
- Clipping, no date, of questions to be asked of former Confederates requesting a pardon. (Folder 2)
- Sermon, no date, of Reverend John Buchanan, rector of St. John's Church, Henrico Parish. The handwriting of the sermon apparently matches Buchanan's handwriting in the St. John's Church Records book, 1730-1860. The sermon is titled "The House of Mourning is to Be Preferred to the House of Feasting." (Folder 2)
- Sermon, [19 September 1819?], of Reverend John Buchanan, rector of St. John's Church, Henrico Parish. The handwriting of the sermon apparently matches Buchanan's handwriting in the St. John's Church Records book, 1730-1860. The sermon is titled "The Blessings of Redeeming Love." (Folder 2)